so let's talk about hindrances in
relation to the wild
animal about the fetas last
time so what do hindrances
do of course they hinder but I mean more
specifically were differently
described why they particularly um well
why do they pertain to the wild animal
not to
you that's also is described as
Corruptions of Mind weakness of wisdom
why what do it
do what does the hindrance do to the
animal wild what do it do wildness no no
what does it do to the
um to your experience as a
whole why is
it what is a hindrance do to the
relationship of uh between you and the
wild obscures it yeah which part
it's the relationship which part of
it I suppose the access like
the capacity to access wild an wild
animal yeah it obscures the wild animal
it obscures the space in between yeah
and makes it muddy makes it cloudy makes
it
colored yeah makes it overlooked
underlooked over intended under
over intended under
intended um so what would be the first
and foremost thing you would do in
regard to any hindrance then to not fall
into overlooking the mind underlook it
missing
it giving the
precepts more more specifically now
that's all taken for granted that you're
already doing that because you wouldn't
be seeing the Mind otherwise no I mean
directly in relation to the
hindrances what can you do when the
hindrance is present the mind is
obscured how do you get it
back don't act out of the
hindrances you don't act out that
obviously would prevent things from
getting worse but it would still not
necessarily remove the hindrance
and at the same time which is also not
immediately removing the hindrance but
you don't try to directly get rid
of the hindrance the hindrance because
that would what does those what does the
what do those two things have in common
so not acting out of a hindrance and not
trying to directly remove the hindrance
what's the common thread for
thread for
both so why would you be acting out of a
hindrance let's let's ask like
that CU you don't want to endure yeah
cuz it's pressuring you anytime it's
painful why you want to be trying to get
rid of the hindrance because the not
wanting to endure the pressure of it
right so both types of actions would
really be rooted in hindrance
yeah so that's the first thing you have
to do if you want to get back to see in
your mind make sure that no act by Body
speech or mind is rooted in hindrance so
how do you make sure that it how how do
you make sure that how do you do
that because whatever you want to attend
to do is rooted in hind in the
hindrance so what do you do
then the basic thing is to question the
motivation the intent behind whatever
you are doing yeah that will reveal it
but what does that lead to then how do
you then address the actual cuz the
hindra is still there in in the way so
to speak MH so you're still not
revealing the
Mind Al as I said you're not making it
worse you're still not revealing it
why so whatever you attend to will be
coming out of
hindrance how' you bypass that what is a
single factor that would remove the
hindering aspect of a hindrance what is
a single thing you can
actually develop correct
attention that is the single reason that
you hindered and that's the single reason
hindered and that's the single reason
that everything you attend to is rooted
in hindrance
because without Yono of your
manikara the Yono of your manasara
becomes a hindrance it's the hindrance
so although you're attending this and
that and counterpart and stuff all of
yice of that is the hindrance so you
want to
push where it's not the
hindrance where it's the
mind so through not acting out of the
pressure of the hindrance you stay on
the level where you know the mind is
even if if you're not seeing it and then
balancing the the womb the inside of
whatever is being attended pushing for
that perspective but for that
context and the mind's there that is
what the mind will
be so although then the tendency to the
hindrance might be still present and if
you um distract yourself from Yara
you become hindered again but you cannot
be hindered for as long as thear is
established impossible doesn't matter
the amount of the pressure of the
hindrance but now that we got it out of
the way yes not allowing pressuring
images to take the center stage would be
one way of reestablishing the
balance not acting out
uh out of the body speech or mind not
giving into the pressure would be
another way with establishing the
balance but the reason is you have to
know that you have to be seeing past the
hindrance through it to be unhindered
not to remove it or deal with
it because you easily kind of especially
when it gets into the sub levels would
fall into kind of a tendency that's
still there to some degree to try to
address it as if like no no no if I
remove this the mind will be seen no the
mind is not seen not because of the
hindrance but because your attention
chose to rest on the hindrance
indirectly as the
basis so that needs to be
bypassed but that's not something you
can directly attend
to it's through that peripheral
knowledge of what you're attending
that's what you then have to work on and
keep looking
further to contain the hindrance rightly
and to not be hindered by
it and then also see like as I said
before sometimes to if desire to see the
mind is too strong well that will be the
reason you won't be seeing the
mind if the intention if the craving is
is is too determined to see it that will
be the reason for obscuring
it so that's why goes handar goes hand
in hand with
knowledge see if you're not overdoing it
what you're left with is well you know
that the space in between is there
whether you attend to it or not whether
you know it whether you're aware of it
or not it has to be there so that
knowledge already reestablishes a degree
of balance now of course within that
you're going to have more subtle
pressures coming up but the principle
Remains the
Same whereas knowledge has to be be
developed to the point of it becomes
unshakable regardless of what what's
being forced what's forcing itself in
between to skute
it so that's that's why mindfulness is
always the basis of like well you can be
doubting and not seeing the mind and all
of this but fundamentally you recollect
the basic context and then you know okay
well it is within this cannot be outside
of this and then just retrace your steps
in that in that
manner so you don't want to be dealing
with hindrances
yourself you want to be basically setting
up the mind to deal with it the animal
so you set it up by not taking it at
face value and acting out and trying to
counter it or get rid of it and then
your work is while the hindrance is
pressuring you to increase the depth of
your Yono let's put it that way so that
the mind is discerned in regard to the
hindrance not like okay it's gone now I
can go back to the mind no no no the
Mind needs to
learn about hindrances in the mind needs
to lose the desire to act out of them
the Mind needs to fundamentally lose
that paa to Avo them to Avo the pressure
of sensuality will restlessness doubt um
sluggishness and so on it's the mind's
problem which obviously makes it a your
problem
so first you don't act out of it so you
don't fall into a
trap uh second you recollect you
remember you revisit the fact that the
mind has to be there even if it's not
seen and that it should not be seen at
the expense of removing a hindrance it
should be seen through the hindrance
so that both are there so to speak and
that's how the mind gets to know about
hindrances and the problem of them well
exactly there won't be hindrance
anymore yeah checking on your intentions
it's another way of regaining
reestablishing the
balance it's like what what why am I
trying to to reestablish the balance of
the mind now is it because I'm not
seeing it really or because I was
pressure by something and I'm just
needing to deal with
it I was like oh well that's why I won't
be balancing it rightly cuz I'm acting
out of such such an
intention so being able to see yourself
doing things yeah that's always that step is
things yeah that's always that step is
the first one and it never disappears it
never ceases you always have to be able
to see yourself doing or not
doing while you're doing it while you're
doing it yeah that's the point after
yeah because it said it said in the
those suit as we mentioned it before as
well in the talks like when um agreeable
perceptions come
up wrongly not attending them with
yis they are a
hindrance when disagreeable perceptions
come up absence of yo they a hindrance
so if they're attended with yo those
things remain is the hindering aspect
it's
G you want to bring up the animal and
clarify it while being pressured that's
how you deal with it rightly that's how
the animal learns to come down in regard
to it and not be agitated by the
presence of hindrances towards these
certain directions of action and so
on and then you can clearly see ah the
possibility of that hindrance is between
the two of
us as in the animals hindered and I
don't see it on account of it if I keep
well you won't be seeing it because you
you'll end up acting out of it and not
paying attention to your actions anymore
but if you don't act out of it doesn't
matter how obscure the animal is you can
always recollect the knowledge that it
has to be
there and then you can then on top of
that recollect the knowledge that you
shouldn't be trying to get rid of the
hindrance that brings you even closer to
the animal and then you can recollect
the knowledge
that attending through the
hindrance brings up the animal while the
hindrance is
there because is the hindrance felt yeah
there you go who feeling the who who is
feeling the hindrance you or the animal
the animal there you go clarify the
feeling of the hindrance you got back
the image of the animal so the only
thing you have to get rid of is is the
action exactly on your part yes and
ignorance on the animal's
part so that's why I mean like it's the
it's about what you do but then also you
got to Now teach the animal the right
course of action as well to not resist
it to not not try to get rid of it to
not um as I said be agitated by the
presence of it they would then push you
try to push towards
action but yes so animal
feels yeah you can't doubt that you can't
yeah you can't doubt that you can't
doubt the feeling you can doubt whether
the animal feels or not but if you would
have not acted out of the pressing
hindrance if you would have maintained
the context OFA you would have
recollected what's being felt there is
the animal feeling the hindrance that
you are now correctly attending all of
it
so simply by feeling the hindrance the
animal is
revealed and through feeling you don't
stop feeling it it's like okay so it's
the animal that needs to deactivate
itself calm down basically to the extent
that it has been agitated by the
hindrance so that's my task it's not to
remove the
hindrance it's to calm the animal while
the hindrance is there repeatedly until
it basically stops being agitated by it
and when the animal is not agitated by
the five
hindrances what happens
then what did the Su say
John yes your mind is
Luminous well it's it's it's safe it's
it's secluded from un wholesome
States so
the animal you seclude the animal not by
hiding it in a in a dungeon but by
teaching it to REM remain immovable
towards the
fire and when it's fully
trained and um
immovable you recognize oh it's actually
quite secluded from anything they used
secluded from anything they used
to bother or agitate it and then you
feel relieved on a conver because
there's no no work for you there
now you could genuinely relax as if you
just pay the big debt as if you just
crossed a massive desert and relieved
that you that everything's fine as if
you were just released from a jail where
you were constantly on
body and then the animal is factually
calm luminous unobstructed trained
so you still have perceptions coming up
thinking and
pondering but none of
those come from a place of
hindrance they would try they're trying
but the animal is equally
movable so none of that can come in
between because again as I said it was
through through agitation of the animal
that these things will be placed in
between
that's what did say I think in one of
the sutas that the first J is besed by
the perceptions of
sensuality but not as a hindrance still
trying to get you well the thoughts they
still have their own
habits and for as long as you know
especially say if the animal is freshly
calm recently calm there's still going
to be maras and habits trying to like
test that but you don't battle those
that but you don't battle those
things you you battle teaching the
animal that's your work not not removal
of these things they come up CU they had
a problem only because animal is
agitated I with if it's
I with if it's
coming with or seen through
it really doesn't matter what it doesn't
matter because there is no um no
obscuring takes place because you remain
detached um detached you remain sort of
uh recipient of the extent mhm of the
animal and your position there and
everything else that comes up it's
within that
so inevitably you know you would be to
some degree falling into acting out of
the hindrances and that's that's the point
hindrances and that's that's the point
like it's not like cuz see it can it can
feel like a daunting task like this hind
keep coming I have to keep dealing with
them every time and but really you don't
deal with
them you only deal with them to the
extent that you've been acting out of
them or they been thinking about acting
out of them yeah that you need to stop
but then you realize I don't need to
deal with the hindrance I just need to
teach the animal to not be agitated and
involved with
it and then the hindrance falls
off in a sense of the animal sort of is
immovable so it doesn't really matter if
something is in between or
not there is no
agitation the animal does not go in
hiding in between meaning like U you
going around your the rest of your day
you're not thinking you know about the
animal but that doesn't matter because
you know that it's depends accessible
depends if you're going around your day
mindfully yeah with clear awareness and
comprehension and the animal is always
the background of your experience that's
fine but if you're going around because
you're pressur by hindrance to go around
then it matters then you're acting
out guess it might be slightly slightly
tangental but um it's reminding me of
um something you were
saying recently is um in regard to like
teaching the
animal how to not be how to be immovable
in regard to hindrances mhm um
because any
hindrance is I'm going to paraphrase
what you said but any hindrance will
have um like one end of it is a sense of
like pressure or some kind of itch let's
say and it will have some
image associated with it that like the animal
associated with it that like the animal
is associating with that with that that
itch or that kind of it wants it kind of
corresponds to
it um and so you are asking like what is
the relationship or is there a Rel
relationship between the sense of
pressure and the
image that it wants to kind of land on
wants to go
forh and the point is that there's a
there's no relationship at all it's a
completely gr's Association yeah yeah
and so then you are asking like
so and if there were like that that's
it's completely gratuitous there is no
possible there's no relationship at all
um and it's only kind
of because it keeps feeding itself and
you keep taking it for granted taking it
for granted you keep taking it for
granted so then you are asking like so
how do you
disassociate stuff
stuff
um yeah so how do you disassociate the
images they want to take the center
stage say when when you pressure by
hindrance of ill will m and images
of anger towards person or whatever want
to occupy want to activate your
mind so how do you disassociate those
images from that
pressure by not attending to
them what does that mean can I attend to
something else yeah so I can distract myself from
else yeah so I can distract myself from
them
well if you're trying to get if you're
attending to something else on account
of trying to get rid of the pressure
then that's obviously that's so how do
you do it
then there's a difference between cuz
that is being hinded that is acting out
of the pressure but but it is possible
to so what's the difference between not
attending and distracting yourself well
you have to include the pressure in that
and then not attend to what the image
that that is so those images are still
there in the background blur as a blur
yeah no yeah no you're right but I want
you to clarify it because you say don't
attend to them aha okay so I'll attend
to something else at the expense of it
it's like yeah don't attend to them to
the extent that you would be involving
yourself with them but not like don't
attend to them get rid of them and
replace them with new sets of images MH
you want to disassociate and you can't
disassociate if you remove the whole
thing so you make sure they don't take the
so you make sure they don't take the
sent stage they remain there as a blur
but you're not feeding the
association of specific images with
centrality specific images with a
will and you're really like I found that
a very good or like it's an important
distinction because like as a
blur like you were saying um you know
you can know exactly what without
sharpening it without focusing on it you
know you know exactly what it will be
but you don't even need to kind of look
into it look into it to any extent and
that's it like that's all you need to
kind of keep it on that level and there
will be no possible continuance of that
Association and and that's that middle
ground that people tend to
overlook you know when the Buddha says
you know he he obliterates he gets rid
of the the thoughts that's how you do it
you do it to the extent that you would
be feeding them you don't do it to the
extent of just replacing them with
something else cuz well you just created
new thoughts and now you're dependent on and
thoughts and now you're dependent on and
you don't recognize where your input
is and he gave countless simulus you
know like the um how to do it rightly
it's like that the turtle and the
Jackal like the turtle is no in no
position to chase the Jackle
away but it is in a position to not
extend its limbs out where the Jackal
would bite it so the Jackal remain there
waiting for its opportunity but the
turtle does not cross the
line does not reach out and then the
Jack leaves that's how those blurring
blurred thoughts would leave you
eventually not cuz you countered them
through perfect management technique but
through exactly not allowing them to
Center Stage which was your
responsibility so that's why when the
suit do describe getting rid of the
stuff they say you get deliv it through
not welcoming not
delighting and as I was saying um back
then even without allowing the specific
images to crystallize in your
mind while it's still the pressuring
blur you know exactly what images will
be crystallized if you were to allow it
even without need to think about it and
that part is your doing oh so no I will
remain enduring the pressure on the
right level
I shall have the bluring possibilities
waiting to be attended to and
crystallized into more but I won't do it
I won't lose the sight of the peripheral
I won't lose the sight of the right
context I won't Whatever Whatever
wherever you anchored you won't lose the
side of that that's your work to that
extent cuz yeah it would be great if
they don't come up in the first place
but you're in no position to make such a
demand and acting out of desire to not
have them come in the the first place
means overreaching for the Jackal to
chase him away and then he bites you so
you remain hooked and
trapped and even when the M was
describing the Buddha he said for six
years he followed him closely follow his
eye everything all every sense every
thought to see if he can find an opening
that he reaches out and he couldn't and
then he gave up
and see another layer to that now in the
context of of this so by not overly
reaching out trying to get rid of things
by not distracting yourself you remain
feeling the pressure and
blur in other words you remain with the
animal even if you don't think it yeah
because that which is felt on that level
of pressure is what animal
feels it's the animal's
feeling well that will eventually become
parent you won't feel like it's animal's
feeling but that is where the animal is
what animal is